<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN" [
<!ENTITY prompt "<prompt>&gt;</prompt><prompt>&gt;</prompt><prompt>&gt;</prompt>">
<!ENTITY prompt2 "<prompt>...</prompt>">
]>

<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <author><firstname>Steven</firstname><surname>Bird</surname></author>
    <authorinitials>sb</authorinitials>
    <author><firstname>Edward</firstname><surname>Loper</surname></author>
    <authorinitials>edl</authorinitials>
    <title>NLTK Tutorial: Chunking</title>
  </articleinfo>

  <section> <title> Introduction </title>

    <para>For many practical purposes it is not necessary to construct
    a complete parse tree for a sentence.  <glossterm>Chunk parsing</glossterm>,
    also known as <glossterm>partial parsing</glossterm>
    <glossterm>light parsing</glossterm>, or just <glossterm>chunking</glossterm>,
    is an approach in which the parser
    assigns incomplete syntactic structure to the phrase.  The most common use
    of chunking is in <glossterm>information extraction</glossterm> and
    <glossterm>message understanding</glossterm>, where the
    content of a text is mind for information that will be used to fill out a
    template.  Chunk parsing is
    actually more like tagging than conventional parsing,
    in the sense that it typically uses
    finite-state methods and employs rules that work directly off the (tagged)
    surface string.  This contrasts with conventional parsing, which normally
    uses context-free rules expressed over abstract categories (e.g. phrasal
    categories).</para>

    <para>In terms of the other NLP tasks, chunking usually takes place after
    tokenization and tagging.</para>

    <para>
    Typically, chunk parsers are based on finite-state methods.
    The constraints about well-formed chunks are expressed using
    regular expressions over the sequence of word tags.
    This tutorial describes the NLTK regular-expression chunk parser.
    </para>

  </section> <!-- Introduction -->

  <section> <title> The Chunk Parser Interface </title>

    <para>Unlike conventional parsers, a chunk parser does not return
    a tree but a simple structure showing where the chunks are.  The
    most transparent Python representation is a list, consisting of a
    mixture of tokens and sublists.  Here is an example of a
    <emphasis>chunk structure</emphasis>:</para>

<programlisting>
[
  [
    'the'/'DT'@[1],
    'cat'/'NN'@[2]
  ],
  'sat'/'VBD'@[3],
  'on'/'IN'@[4],
  [
    'the'/'DT'@[5],
    'mat'/'NN'@[6]
  ]
]
</programlisting>

    <para>Thus, a chunker takes a list of tokens, and produces a list of
    (lists of) tokens.  This generalization about chunkers is expressed
    in the
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.chunkparser.ChunkParserI.html">
    <literal>ChunkParserI</literal></ulink> class.</para>

    <note><para>Note that this definition of chunk structure is too weak to
    express a more general kind of chunking which associates a type to each
    chunk.  For example, there are chunkers which can identify both
    NP and VP chunks.  For these it is necessary to define a more expressive
    representation.</para></note>

    <para>All chunk parsers, including the <literal>REChunkParser</literal>
    class discussed below, should inherit from <literal>ChunkParserI</literal>
    and reimplement its <literal>parse</literal> method.
    </para>

  </section> <!-- The Chunk Parser Interface -->

  <section> <title> The Chunking Tokenizer </title>

    <para>A common file representation for chunked tagged text is as
    follows:</para>

<programlisting>
[ the/DT little/JJ cat/NN ]
sat/VBD on/IN
[ the/DT mat/NN ]
</programlisting>

    <para>It is often useful to be able to tokenize
    text input in this format as part of the evaluation process.
    For this purpose, the 
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.token.html">
    <literal>token</literal></ulink>
    module contains a special kind of tagged tokenizer class, the
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.token.ChunkedTaggedTokenizer.html">
    <literal>ChunkTaggedTokenizer</literal></ulink>.</para>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>correct_sent = """
[ the/DT little/JJ cat/NN ]
sat/VBD on/IN
[ the/DT mat/NN ]</command>
"""

&prompt; <command>tokenizer = ChunkedTaggedTokenizer()</command>
&prompt; <command>correct_chunks = tokenizer.tokenize(correct_sent)</command>
[['the'/'DT'@[1word], 'little'/'JJ'@[2word], 'cat'/'NN'@[3word]],
'sat'/'VBD'@[5word], 'on'/'IN'@[6word], ['the'/'DT'@[8word], 'mat'/'NN'@[9word]]]
</programlisting>
    
    <para>Another utility defined in the <literal>rechunkparser</literal>
    module,
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.rechunkparser.unchunk.html">
    <literal>unchunk</literal></ulink>
    allows the chunking to be removed:</para>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>unchunked_sent = unchunk(correct_chunks)</command>
['the'/'DT'@[1word], 'little'/'JJ'@[2word], 'cat'/'NN'@[3word], 'sat'/'VBD'@[5word],
'on'/'IN'@[6word], 'the'/'DT'@[8word], 'mat'/'NN'@[9word]]
</programlisting>

  </section> <!-- The Chunking Tokenizer -->

  <section> <title> The String Representation of Tokenized Sequences </title>

    <para>Before we can apply a regular expression to a sequence of objects,
    those objects must first be encoded in a string.  This presents a difficulty.
    We want to apply the chunker to the output of the tagger, and we want the
    output of the chunker simply add the chunking information.  However, on
    the face of it, we must first project out the tags into a string, chunk
    the string, then somehow get back to the non-string representation.  The
    following sequence of Python objects illustrate the dilemma:</para>

<programlisting>
<emphasis># tagger output</emphasis>
[ 'the'/'DT'@[1], 'cat'/'NN'@[2] 'sat'/'VBD'@[3], 'on'/'IN'@[4],
'the'/'DT'@[5], 'mat'/'NN'@[6] ]

<emphasis># the list of tags</emphasis>
[ 'DT', 'NN', 'VBD', 'IN', 'DT', 'NN' ]

<emphasis># the string of tags ready for chunking</emphasis>
'DT NN VBD IN DT NN'

<emphasis># the chunked tags</emphasis>
'[DT NN] VBD IN [DT NN]'

<emphasis># some black magic?</emphasis>
[ [ 'the'/'DT'@[1], 'cat'/'NN'@[2] ], 'sat'/'VBD'@[3], 'on'/'IN'@[4],
[ 'the'/'DT'@[5],'mat'/'NN'@[6] ] ]
</programlisting>

    <para>The solution is to encode each token in a string which contains sufficient
    information for the token to be reconstructed, and then write chunking rules
    which only consider the tags, ignoring the types and the locations.
    The <literal>REChunkParser</literal> class provides a convenient interface
    hides this additional layer of complexity from the developer.</para>

    <para>The string representation of a token is illustrated below:</para>

<programlisting>
<emphasis># a token</emphasis>
'the'/'DT'@[1]

<emphasis># the string encoding</emphasis>
'&gt;the/DT@[1]&lt;'
</programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>rechunkparser</literal> module provides a function
    <literal>tag2str</literal> which takes a list of tagged tokens and converts
    it into a string, concatenating the string encoding of each token.</para>

    <note><para>Note that no spaces are inserted between the encoded tokens.
    In the encoding, tokens are delimited with &lt; and &gt;, not with
    whitespace.</para></note>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>ttokens = [ 'the'/'DT'@[1], 'cat'/'NN'@[2] 'sat'/'VBD'@[3],
'on'/'IN'@[4], 'the'/'DT'@[5], 'mat'/'NN'@[6] ]</command>
&prompt; <command>tag2str(ttokens)</command>
'&lt;the/DT@[1]&gt;&lt;cat/NN@[2]&gt;&lt;sat/VBD@[3]&gt;&lt;on/IN@[4]&gt;&lt;the/DT@[5]&gt;&lt;mat/NN@[6]&gt;'
</programlisting>

    <para>The chunker operates on this string, not by splitting it, but
    by inserting/removing chunk delimiters.  The <literal>rechunkparser</literal>
    module uses braces as delimiters since, unlike parentheses and square brackets, these
    do not usually need to be backslash-escaped in regular expressions.
    Thus, the chunked representation of the above example is as follows:
    </para>

<programlisting>
'{&lt;the/DT@[1]&gt;&lt;cat/NN@[2]&gt;}&lt;sat/VBD@[3]&gt;&lt;on/IN@[4]&gt;{&lt;the/DT@[5]&gt;&lt;mat/NN@[6]&gt;}'
</programlisting>

    <para>The module provides a method called <literal>str2chunks</literal>
    which builds a chunk structure from this string.  This is what is
    returned by the chunkparser for further processing, e.g. by an
    information extraction system.</para>

    <para>It is possible to build an NLTK chunker based solely on the
    infrastructure provided above.  However, we also provide classes to
    make it easier to express chunk rules and chunk parsers.  The
    rest of the section discusses these.</para>

    </section> <!-- The String Representation of Tokenized Sequences -->

    <section> <title> Chunk Rules and Abstract Chunk Rules </title>

    <para>Chunk rules operate on strings of encoded tokens to insert
    and delete the chunk delimiters.  For instance, a rule might
    create a chunk by inserting <literal>{</literal> before the fifth
    token, and inserting <literal>}</literal> after the sixth token.
    Equally, a rule could combine two adjacent chunks by
    <emphasis>removing</emphasis> <literal>}{</literal> from the string.</para>

    <para>The
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.rechunkparser.ChunkRule.html">
    <literal>ChunkRule</literal></ulink> class provides a convenient wrapper
    for Python's built-in <literal>re</literal> (regular expression) class.
    The <literal>ChunkRule</literal> constructor takes five arguments:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>target</emphasis>
        The material that the regular expression must apply to
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>action</emphasis>
        The action performed on this material
        (i.e. reproducing the material using the <literal>\1</literal>
        construct and adding or removing braces).
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>left</emphasis>
        The left-hand context in which this rule applies.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>right</emphasis>
        The right-hand context in which this rule applies.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>doc</emphasis>
        Brief documentation of the function of the rule
        (e.g. <literal>'chunking groups of JJ|NN'</literal>).
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Both <literal>target</literal> and <literal>action</literal>
    are explicit arguments.  The remaining arguments are optional,
    keyword arguments.  Here is a chunk rule which inserts the chunk
    delimiters around any tag <literal>NN</literal>.</para>

<programlisting>
ChunkRule(r'(&lt;[^&gt;]*/NN@[^&gt;]*&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk NNs')
</programlisting>

    <note><para>Note that we use Python's raw string notation, so that
    the interpreter does not preprocess the backslash escapes.  In general,
    it is a good idea to use the raw string notation whenever regular
    expressions are involved.  We follow this practice here.</para></note>

    <para>This rule matches tokens like
    <literal>&lt;cat/NN@[1]&gt;</literal>,
    and flags them as chunks by wrapping them with the chunk
    delimiters.  This is probably the simplest kind of chunk rule,
    and it is already incomprehensible.  Therefore, the
    <literal>rechunkparser</literal> module defines a more
    convenient interface, namely the <literal>AbstractChunkRule</literal>
    class.</para>

    <para>The
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.rechunkparser.AbstractChunkRule.html">
    <literal>AbstractChunkRule</literal></ulink>
    class is a simple wrapper for the <literal>ChunkRule</literal> class.
    <literal>AbstractChunkRule</literal> is a derived class whose
    initializer preprocesses its <literal>target</literal>,
    <literal>left</literal> and <literal>right</literal> arguments.
    The calling function can now employ regular expressions
    <emphasis>over the tags only</emphasis>,
    ignoring the fact that the string also contains types and
    locations.  The chunk rule we saw above can now be written
    as follows:</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;NN&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk NNs')
</programlisting>

    <para>Given this simpler format it is now relatively straightforward
    to construct some quite complex chunk rules.  The first generalization
    is to note that the tags themselves have some internal structure that
    we can exploit.  For example, a plural noun is tagged <literal>NNS</literal>.
    Suppose we wished to treat all tags starting with <literal>NN</literal>
    in a single chunk rule.  We could do this as follows:</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;NN.*&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk NNX')
</programlisting>

    <para>In some cases, there is no common prefix and so we are forced
    to use disjunction.  Here is a chunk rule which puts chunk delimiters
    around any individual determiner, adjective or noun.  (Adjacent chunks would then
    need to be merged by another rule.)</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;DT|JJ|NN.*&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk DT|JJ|NNX')
</programlisting>

    <para>Now suppose we wished to create a single chunk which encompassed
    a sequence consisting of a determiner followed by zero or more adjectives,
    followed by a noun.  We can also use the star operator for this:</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN.*&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk DT,JJ,NNX')
</programlisting>

    <para>In this example, the scope of the star operator is the preceding tag
    (i.e. the material contained inside the previous pair of angle brackets).
    </para>

    <note><para>Note that the star and other regular expression operators
    behave differently depending on whether they are inside or outside the
    scope of the angle brackets.  Inside the angle brackets, the operators work
    at the character level.  Outside the angle brackets the operators apply to
    complete tags.  In other words, the angle brackets are behaving like
    ordinary parentheses in regular expressions.</para></note>

    <para>The application of chunk rules can be constrained by making use of
    the <literal>left</literal> and <literal>right</literal> context arguments.
    For example, suppose we wanted to chunk a maximal string of tags which ends
    with a verb.  Here is a possible rule:</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;.*&gt;*)', r'{\1}', right = r'&lt;VB.*&gt;')
</programlisting>

    <note><para>Contrary to the above, for technical reasons it is
    <emphasis>not</emphasis> possible to use the left context in
    <literal>AbstractChunkRule</literal>s.  (This is because Python's
    look-behind operator requires a fixed-width pattern.)</para></note>

    <note><para>We use a special context argument to permit rules to apply
    to their own output.  The other logical possibility - embedding
    multiple parentheses in the <literal>target</literal> argument, prevents
    rules reapplying to the same context.  This is only an issue in those
    cases where the context of some rule later becomes the target of a
    separate instance of the same rule.</para></note>

    </section> <!-- Chunk Rules and Abstract Chunk Rules -->

    <section> <title> The REChunkParser Class </title>

    <para>The
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.rechunkparser.REChunkParser.html">
    <literal>REChunkParser</literal></ulink>
    allows the programmer to construct a chunkparser object from a list
    (or <emphasis>cascade</emphasis>) of chunk rules.  Suppose we have a list of
    of rules and a list of tokens.  Then we can construct
    a chunkparser and apply it as follows:</para>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>chunker = REChunkParser(rules)</command>
&prompt; <command>chunker.parse(tokens)</command>
</programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>parse</literal> method converts its argument to the
    string encoding, applies the chunk rules in sequence, then converts the
    result to a chunk structure and returns this structure.  Here is a
    simple example using a rule we created earlier:</para>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>r1 = AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc="chunking &lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN&gt;")</command>
&prompt; <command>cp = REChunkParser([r1])</command>
&prompt; <command>chunked_sent = cp.parse(unchunked_sent)</command>
[['the'/'DT'@[1word], 'little'/'JJ'@[2word], 'cat'/'NN'@[3word]],
'sat'/'VBD'@[5word], 'on'/'IN'@[6word], ['the'/'DT'@[8word], 'mat'/'NN'@[9word]]]
</programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>REChunkParser</literal> initializer has an optional
    second argument which is a debug flag.  If this is set (e.g. to 1) then
    the chunk parser will display diagnostic output.  We repeat the above
    example with the debug flag set:</para>

<programlisting>
&prompt; <command>r1 = AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN&gt;)', r'{\1}', doc="chunking &lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN&gt;")</command>
&prompt; <command>cp = REChunkParser([r1], 1)</command>
&prompt; <command>chunked_sent = cp.parse(unchunked_sent)</command>

chunking &lt;DT&gt;&lt;JJ&gt;*&lt;NN&gt;:
left:
target: ((?:&lt;[^/]*/(?:DT)@\d+&gt;)(?:&lt;[^/]*/(?:JJ)@\d+&gt;)*(?:&lt;[^/]*/(?:NN)@\d+&gt;))
right:
action: {\1}
input:   &lt;DT&gt;  &lt;JJ&gt;  &lt;NN&gt;  &lt;VBD&gt;  &lt;IN&gt;  &lt;DT&gt;  &lt;NN&gt;
   -&gt;   {&lt;DT&gt;  &lt;JJ&gt;  &lt;NN&gt;} &lt;VBD&gt;  &lt;IN&gt; {&lt;DT&gt;  &lt;NN&gt;}
</programlisting>

    </section> <!-- The REChunkParser Class -->

    <section> <title> Chunking Strategies </title>

    <para>brute force vs iterative</para>

    <para>Notes: in the brute force approach we construct complex
    regular expressions which create the desired chunks in a single step.
    In the iterative approach we create chunks, then successively merge
    and split them, until we get the desired result.</para>

    <para>chunking vs chinking</para>

    <para>Notes: chunking begins with an unchunked sentence and adds chunk
    delimiters.  The dual approach, known as <emphasis>chinking</emphasis>
    begins with the entire sentence in a single chunk, then removes pieces.
    For example, we could chunk the whole sentence then
    chink the verbs using the following rule:</para>

<programlisting>
AbstractChunkRule(r'(.*)', r'{\1}', doc='chunk the entire sentence')
AbstractChunkRule(r'(&lt;VB.*&gt;)', r'}\1{', doc='chink the verbs')
</programlisting>

    <para>Note the directionality of the braces in the second argument
    of the second constructor.</para>
    
  </section> <!-- Chunking Strategies -->

  <section> <title> Evaluating Chunk Parsers </title>

    <para> An easy way to evaluate a chunk parser is to take some
    already chunked text, strip off the chunks, rechunk it, and compare
    the result with the original chunked text.  NLTK provides the necessary
    functions:</para>

<programlisting>
unchunked_sent = unchunk(correct_chunks)
chunker = REChunkParser(rules)
chunked_sent = cp.parse(unchunked_sent)
score(correct_chunks, chunked_sent)
</programlisting>

    <para>The 
    <ulink url="http://nltk.sourceforge.net/ref/nltk.rechunkparser.score.html">
    <literal>score</literal></ulink>
    function takes the correctly chunked sentence as its first argument, and
    the newly chunked version as its second argument, and compares them.
    It reports the fraction of actual chunks that were found (recall), the
    fraction of hypothesized chunks that were correct (precision), and a
    combined score, the F-measure (the harmonic mean of precision and recall).
    </para>

  </section> <!-- Evaluating Chunk Parsers -->

</article>
